<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: programming | philcrissman.com]]></title>
  <link href="http://philcrissman.com/blog/categories/programming/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://philcrissman.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-11-28T09:16:31-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://philcrissman.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Phil Crissman]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Alternate FizzBuzz Solution]]></title>
    <link href="http://philcrissman.com/2012/11/28/alternate-fizzbuzz-solution/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-28T08:56:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://philcrissman.com/2012/11/28/alternate-fizzbuzz-solution</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you aren't familiar with what 'FizzBuzz' refers to, see <a href="http://c2.com/cgi/wiki?FizzBuzzTest">http://c2.com/cgi/wiki?FizzBuzzTest</a>.</p>

<p><strong>Q</strong>: So here is a description of the 'FizzBuzz' problem. Do you think you could give us a quick solution for this?</p>

<p><strong>A</strong>: Sure, that looks pretty simple. I can solve it any way I like?</p>

<p><strong>Q</strong>: Of course.</p>

<p><strong>A</strong>: Great. Well, I'll start by writing a unit test.</p>

<p><strong>Q</strong>: ... Well, that probably isn't necessary...</p>

<p><strong>A</strong>: Maybe not, but I want to be able to instantly verify the solution. Let's see. Well, to test the output, I'll need a reference string. <em>[Begins writing]</em> Something to compare the output to show that it's correct... So, like, "1 2 Fizz 4 Buzz Fizz 7 8 Fizz Buzz 11 Fizz 13 14 FizzBuzz..." <em>[Continues writing]</em></p>

<p><strong>Q</strong>: Well... Okay...</p>

<p><strong>A</strong>: Does this look right? <em>[Displays finished string of numbers 1..100 with Fizz &amp; Buzz appropriately inserted]</em> As in, if our output matches this, we'll have a successful program?</p>

<p><strong>Q</strong>: Sure, that looks correct, but...</p>

<p><strong>A</strong>: Great. Now let's write our function. Here's our method; we'd run the test here and watch it fail. Now, just to make it green, I'll just have the method output our reference string.</p>

<p><strong>Q</strong>: ...</p>

<p><strong>A</strong>: Say, this actually fulfills the requirements right now. I guess I'm done.</p>

<p><strong>Q</strong>: But you actually haven't written anything to programmatically produce the FizzBuzz string!</p>

<p><strong>A</strong>: True, but since we already have a string which we've agreed is the correct result, if we just output that string, we'll satisfy the requirements for the problem. So, I'd say we're done.</p>

<p><strong>Q</strong>: But what if we wanted to see the results from 1 to 10,000?</p>

<p><strong>A</strong>: Well, gee. <em>That</em> wasn't in the requirements.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
