<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: mind | philcrissman.com]]></title>
  <link href="http://philcrissman.com/blog/categories/mind/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://philcrissman.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-11-08T11:32:06-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://philcrissman.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Phil Crissman]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Sometimes you need to ignore your mind]]></title>
    <link href="http://philcrissman.com/2012/10/19/sometimes-you-need-to-ignore-your-mind/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-19T15:39:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://philcrissman.com/2012/10/19/sometimes-you-need-to-ignore-your-mind</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/posts/45lb_plate.jpg" title="45 lbs" alt="45 lbs" /></p>

<p>Some time ago, if you had told me that overcoming my mind would be a big factor in working out a the gym, I probably wouldn't have agreed. Oh, I may have <em>assented</em>, but, you know; really? My mind? Other than just getting myself out of bed and <em>into</em> the gym, I wouldn't have seen how it mattered.</p>

<p>I realized the other day how much it does matter.</p>

<p>I'm doing a fairly straightforward workout regimen at the moment; for most exercises, I simply add 5 lbs each session (until stalling, of course, at which point I'll stick to that weight until I can meet my target reps). This morning, adding 5 lbs to my bench press lift meant going to 135 lbs.</p>

<p>About 5 days ago, I benched with 130 lbs, and did all my sets to all my reps. So, what: 5 extra pounds? Doesn't seem like a big deal.</p>

<p>Except that, when you move to 135 lbs on a barbell, you move to putting one single 45 lb plate on each side (the bar itself is 45 lbs). For some reason, when there were several smaller plates on each side, my mind could look at the barbell and think, <em>sure. I can lift that.</em></p>

<p>But with one, large, 45 lb plate (the largest plate you find in any barbell system), my brain thought: <em>2 45lb plates, plus the barbell? That looks heavy. I don't know if I can lift that. In fact, I bet I can't.</em></p>

<p>Mind.</p>

<p>I had to literally ignore the plates, and just look at the bit of barbell above my head and tell myself, this is just 5lbs more than I lifted a few days ago. A few days ago, I had no trouble. This will be no trouble, either.</p>

<p>5 sets later, all reps complete, it was actually no trouble at all.</p>

<p>Now, you may be thinking that 135lbs isn't a very heavy bench. You may be right. Except that I haven't been working out, seriously, for all that long, and bench has not traditionally been an exercise I've been strong in. As far as I was concerned, the barbell with a 45 lb plate on each side was a milestone. I may have lifted it before, but not for several sets, each set meeting my target reps. So it isn't about how much I can bench at this point, but that my mind, for <em>no rational reason other than the large plates <strong>looked</strong> heavier</em>, was trying to tell me I couldn't lift it.</p>

<p>Point being not how much my bench press is or isn't. I finally see how big a part your brain plays, even in pursuits that you might normally think of as 100% physical. I can see how this could apply to a lot of things. Can I bike for 10 miles? Sure, I can do that. How about 20? Sure. 30? 50? 100? Now, if I were to try to go straight from biking 10 miles to 100, nope: probably not. My brain will balk and truthfully, my brain might be correct. But if I were I work my way up to that... If I could bike 30 miles, could I do 50? If I could do 50, how about 75? I think you still need to proceed in reasonable steps. Partly because yeah, you actually <em>do</em> need to work your body up to these things. I couldn't come back next week and bench 300lbs just by thinking "I can do it!" But also to give yourself ammunition to overcome your brain's objections, so that when you think you can't, you can reasonably argue with yourself that you can.</p>

<p>There are going to be times when the truth is, you <em>can</em> do [whatever], but you're brain is telling you that you <em>can't</em>.</p>

<p>That's when you need to ignore your brain.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
