<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: self-improvement | philcrissman.com]]></title>
  <link href="http://philcrissman.com/blog/categories/self-improvement/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://philcrissman.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-04-08T08:03:31-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://philcrissman.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Phil Crissman]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A year from now, you'll look back at your current self and realize you're an idiot]]></title>
    <link href="http://philcrissman.com/2013/01/08/a-year-from-now/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-08T10:25:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://philcrissman.com/2013/01/08/a-year-from-now</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A recurring realization throughout my childhood was looking back at the things I had done or said or been interested in the year or years prior, and cringing to myself; being alternatively amused, ashamed, or dismayed by the sort of things I had thought or done. At nine, I thought 8-year old me was a bit of a doofus. At 10, I realized that 9-year old me was still a bit goofy. At 13, I figured out that pre-teen me was not very cool. At 15, I thought 13-year old me was a bit of a sycophant (disclosure: I don't think I actually knew the word "sycophant" when I was 15). In my 20s, I thought teenage-me was totally clueless. By my late 20s, I saw that that period of cluelessness should be expanded to include my early 20s.</p>

<p>And so on.</p>

<p>Through today. Even looking back a few years ago, I'm bemused by things I may have thought or said, or dismayed by thoughts of how I could have handled given situations in a better way.</p>

<p>What's hardest to realize is that, a year or two from now, I'll look back at me <em>today</em> and see all (a lot of) the ways in which I'm currently being an idiot.</p>

<p>Why is this?</p>

<p>Eric Barker talks a bit about it <a href="http://www.bakadesuyo.com/2013/01/person-expect-be/">here</a>, which is what reminded me about this. But this is something I think about periodically, which hopefully prevents me from believing that I've become too smart: in a year, or a little more, I'll realize all too well just how smart I'm <em>not</em> right now.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
