<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[philcrissman.com]]></title>
  <link href="http://philcrissman.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://philcrissman.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-11-05T12:05:51-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://philcrissman.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Phil Crissman]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Picky]]></title>
    <link href="http://philcrissman.com/2012/11/05/picky/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-05T11:58:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://philcrissman.com/2012/11/05/picky</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Picky is a category search engine for Ruby.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The future we will create]]></title>
    <link href="http://philcrissman.com/2012/10/24/the-future-we-will-create/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-24T16:56:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://philcrissman.com/2012/10/24/the-future-we-will-create</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://philcrissman.com/images/posts/the-future.jpg" title="vintage futurism" alt="The future we will create" /></p>

<p>I&#8217;m in.</p>

<p><a href="http://thisisnthappiness.com/image/34205145682">via</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[They came from another galaxy. So they were a bit tired.]]></title>
    <link href="http://philcrissman.com/2012/10/24/they-came-from-another-galaxy-so-they-were-a-bit-tired/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-24T09:17:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://philcrissman.com/2012/10/24/they-came-from-another-galaxy-so-they-were-a-bit-tired</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://philcrissman.com/images/posts/ibdm-poster.jpg" title="and boy are my arms tired" alt="I just flew in from another galaxy" /></p>

<p><a href="http://www.ibelieveinadv.com/2010/12/h-57-creative-station-intercontinental-ballistic-design-missile-project/">via</a></p>

<p>Found this somewhere in my bookmarks. I just like design, I guess.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What I want to know]]></title>
    <link href="http://philcrissman.com/2012/10/20/what-i-want-to-know/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-20T10:22:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://philcrissman.com/2012/10/20/what-i-want-to-know</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://philcrissman.com/images/posts/calvin_on_school.jpg" title="What I want to know" alt="What I want to know" /></p>

<p><a href="http://thisisnthappiness.com/post/33882373193/calvin-and-hobbes">via</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Sometimes you need to ignore your mind]]></title>
    <link href="http://philcrissman.com/2012/10/19/sometimes-you-need-to-ignore-your-mind/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-19T15:39:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://philcrissman.com/2012/10/19/sometimes-you-need-to-ignore-your-mind</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://philcrissman.com/images/posts/45lb_plate.jpg" title="45 lbs" alt="45 lbs" /></p>

<p>Some time ago, if you had told me that overcoming my mind would be a big factor in working out a the gym, I probably wouldn&#8217;t have agreed. Oh, I may have <em>assented</em>, but, you know; really? My mind? Other than just getting myself out of bed and <em>into</em> the gym, I wouldn&#8217;t have seen how it mattered.</p>

<p>I realized the other day how much it does matter.</p>

<p>I&#8217;m doing a fairly straightforward workout regimen at the moment; for most exercises, I simply add 5 lbs each session (until stalling, of course, at which point I&#8217;ll stick to that weight until I can meet my target reps). This morning, adding 5 lbs to my bench press lift meant going to 135 lbs.</p>

<p>About 5 days ago, I benched with 130 lbs, and did all my sets to all my reps. So, what: 5 extra pounds? Doesn&#8217;t seem like a big deal.</p>

<p>Except that, when you move to 135 lbs on a barbell, you move to putting one single 45 lb plate on each side (the bar itself is 45 lbs). For some reason, when there were several smaller plates on each side, my mind could look at the barbell and think, <em>sure. I can lift that.</em></p>

<p>But with one, large, 45 lb plate (the largest plate you find in any barbell system), my brain thought: <em>2 45lb plates, plus the barbell? That looks heavy. I don&#8217;t know if I can lift that. In fact, I bet I can&#8217;t.</em></p>

<p>Mind.</p>

<p>I had to literally ignore the plates, and just look at the bit of barbell above my head and tell myself, this is just 5lbs more than I lifted a few days ago. A few days ago, I had no trouble. This will be no trouble, either.</p>

<p>5 sets later, all reps complete, it was actually no trouble at all.</p>

<p>Now, you may be thinking that 135lbs isn&#8217;t a very heavy bench. You may be right. Except that I haven&#8217;t been working out, seriously, for all that long, and bench has not traditionally been an exercise I&#8217;ve been strong in. As far as I was concerned, the barbell with a 45 lb plate on each side was a milestone. I may have lifted it before, but not for several sets, each set meeting my target reps. So it isn&#8217;t about how much I can bench at this point, but that my mind, for <em>no rational reason other than the large plates <strong>looked</strong> heavier</em>, was trying to tell me I couldn&#8217;t lift it.</p>

<p>Point being not how much my bench press is or isn&#8217;t. I finally see how big a part your brain plays, even in pursuits that you might normally think of as 100% physical. I can see how this could apply to a lot of things. Can I bike for 10 miles? Sure, I can do that. How about 20? Sure. 30? 50? 100? Now, if I were to try to go straight from biking 10 miles to 100, nope: probably not. My brain will balk and truthfully, my brain might be correct. But if I were I work my way up to that&#8230; If I could bike 30 miles, could I do 50? If I could do 50, how about 75? I think you still need to proceed in reasonable steps. Partly because yeah, you actually <em>do</em> need to work your body up to these things. I couldn&#8217;t come back next week and bench 300lbs just by thinking &#8220;I can do it!&#8221; But also to give yourself ammunition to overcome your brain&#8217;s objections, so that when you think you can&#8217;t, you can reasonably argue with yourself that you can.</p>

<p>There are going to be times when the truth is, you <em>can</em> do [whatever], but you&#8217;re brain is telling you that you <em>can&#8217;t</em>.</p>

<p>That&#8217;s when you need to ignore your brain.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Punk Rock]]></title>
    <link href="http://philcrissman.com/2012/10/16/punk-rock/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-16T08:35:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://philcrissman.com/2012/10/16/punk-rock</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://philcrissman.com/images/posts/usedtobepunkrock.jpg" title="I used to be punk rock" alt="I used to be punk rock" /></p>

<p>I&#8217;m not sure I ever was punk rock. On the other hand, I&#8217;m not sure I ever stopped.</p>

<p>It&#8217;s complicated. It probably depends who you ask.</p>

<p>For me, the entire idea of punk rock isn&#8217;t about the aesthetic, though there was a time when I sort of &#8220;fit&#8221; that mold (viz, &#8220;We all wear a uniform&#8221;, Frank Zappa). It isn&#8217;t about the politics. It isn&#8217;t even (completely) about the music, as I <em>love</em> a lot of music that the original punk rock movement sort of rose up as a reaction against (John Lydon/Johnny Rotten was infamously reported to be discovered by Malcolm McLaren wearing a homemade <em>I hate Pink Floyd</em> t-shirt), though I do love a lot of punk rock music. What I really love about punk rock music is the backbone of integrity that it aspires to&mdash;at least, in my mind. A lot of people, among them folks who are &#8220;really&#8221; punk rock, might not see it the same way.</p>

<p>I think of it as distilling the entire notion of why I do what I do; why you do what you do, why anyone does what they do. In my mind, the motivation implicit in a &#8220;punk rock&#8221; mentality is that, I&#8217;m really not doing this for you. If you like it, that&#8217;s great, and we can have this bond over this shared like of this thing that we&#8217;re doing, but I didn&#8217;t do it so you would like it. That oversimplifies, because sure, if you&#8217;re producing things, whomever you see as &#8220;your people&#8221;, yes, <em>of course</em> you hope that they like it. At least, I do. But at the same time, if you let other people&#8217;s opinions be the sole barometer of the value of your work, I think you wind up with some blank, insipid creation that takes no risks and says nothing, and yeah, no one will like it anyways. Better to do something that at least <em>you</em> like, and then if only a handful of other people like it, at least it&#8217;s genuine.</p>

<p>This makes me think of the whole idea of &#8220;selling out&#8221;. Talking about this is a sure-fire way to stir people up. For some folks, simply &#8220;being successful&#8221; is synonymous with &#8220;selling out&#8221;, which I think is (rightfully) seen as a pretty silly stance by most people. In my mind, it has more to do with <em>what were you willing to change in order to be successful</em>? Is this dumb, old fashioned? Don&#8217;t we want success, at any cost? I don&#8217;t know, but I think most people would say &#8220;no&#8221;.</p>

<p>At the other extreme, I think some people think that there is no such thing as &#8220;selling out&#8221;: no one should ever have their success criticized or impinged with accusations of lost integrity or compromised principles. It&#8217;s none of our business, some would say. I can see that, in most cases, but I don&#8217;t totally buy that, either. I&#8217;m not going to bring up examples, because I don&#8217;t want to derail the discussion into a debate or who really <em>did</em> or <em>did not</em> &#8220;sell out&#8221;&mdash;but I can certainly think of bands who I stopped listening to, not because they became popular, but because the things they changed about their music on the way to becoming popular so completely altered their music as to make them into a completely different band; not the same band I had originally loved. It&#8217;s not really just about &#8220;bands&#8221;, though; anything can have integrity, and anything that has integrity can also lose it.</p>

<p>The idea of punk rock as an analogy to <em>integrity</em> might not be a usual association for most people, but it&#8217;s incredibly valid to me. To me, the whole emotional impact of the phrase &#8220;I used to be punk rock&#8221; isn&#8217;t &#8220;I used to have a mohawk and a safety pin in my ear, but now I don&#8217;t&#8221;&mdash;it more says, &#8220;I used to have integrity, but now I don&#8217;t&#8221;. I realize this is a somewhat revisionist interpretation of &#8220;punk rock&#8221;. One could just as easily say that &#8220;punk rock&#8221; ought to be associated with ideas of nihilism, anarchy, apathy, or rebellion. But ultimately, those aren&#8217;t the things that I associate with &#8216;being punk rock&#8217;.</p>

<p>Whatever.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[High Society]]></title>
    <link href="http://philcrissman.com/2012/10/12/high-society/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-12T12:20:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://philcrissman.com/2012/10/12/high-society</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://philcrissman.com/images/posts/cerebus-high-society-wallpaper.jpg" title="Cerebus -- High Society" alt="High Society" /></p>

<p>I think I mentioned already that I&#8217;ve been rereading Cerebus comics. The first time I read them, I never did get my hands on &#8221;<a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/0919359078/ref=as_li_ss_til?tag=idepermin-20&amp;camp=0&amp;creative=0&amp;linkCode=as4&amp;creativeASIN=0919359078&amp;adid=01FA6RVVXWRQRRTR8DQV&amp;">High Society</a>&#8221; or &#8221;<a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/0919359094/ref=as_li_ss_til?tag=idepermin-20&amp;camp=0&amp;creative=0&amp;linkCode=as4&amp;creativeASIN=0919359094&amp;adid=1NEE9ZRHV08T9JNTKZXE&amp;">Church and State</a>&#8221;; I had read the first volume out of a library, and then started with &#8220;Jaka&#8217;s Story&#8221; through &#8220;Melmoth&#8221; and most of the &#8220;Mothers &amp; Daughters&#8221; story line. Then I fell off the bus for a bit. I&#8217;ve now caught up to about issue 226 (part way through &#8220;Rick&#8217;s Story&#8221;). So, I&#8217;m well past &#8220;re-reading&#8221; and have moved on to just &#8220;reading&#8221;. Looking forward to the conclusion (the entire run of Cerebus is 300 issues, an amazing accomplishment by a single creative team).</p>

<p>Sim&#8217;s a fantastic artist, as is his co-conspirator Gerhard, and a great story-teller, both visually and simply in prose (there&#8217;s a lot of straight prose in certain parts of Cerebus). Well worth a read.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Dress for the job you want]]></title>
    <link href="http://philcrissman.com/2012/10/12/dress-for-the-job-you-want/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-12T12:07:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://philcrissman.com/2012/10/12/dress-for-the-job-you-want</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://philcrissman.com/images/posts/batmans.jpg" title="Batmans" alt="Batmen" /></p>

<p>Dress for the job you want, not the job you have.</p>

<p>Image via <a href="http://ffffound.com/image/ac94fa122d849cb0615ba3fbb8b319f02ee90e86">ffffound</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[We're only in it for the money]]></title>
    <link href="http://philcrissman.com/2012/10/11/were-only-in-it-for-the-money/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-11T09:44:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://philcrissman.com/2012/10/11/were-only-in-it-for-the-money</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://philcrissman.com/images/posts/fz_the_money.jpg" title="A subtle reference" alt="Frank Zappa and the Mothers -- We're Only In It For the Money" /></p>

<p>Those starry-eyed idealists, Frank Zappa and the Mothers of Invention.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Arnold's Blueprint]]></title>
    <link href="http://philcrissman.com/2012/10/10/arnolds-blueprint/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-10T13:58:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://philcrissman.com/2012/10/10/arnolds-blueprint</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I saw this a week or two ago, and never even thought about posting it. But it&#8217;s really relevant to everything else I&#8217;ve been thinking and writing about, so I thought I&#8217;d add it here.</p>

<div class="video-container">
  <script src="http://player.espn.com/player.js?&playerBrandingId=4ef8000cbaf34c1687a7d9a26fe0e89e&pcode=1kNG061cgaoolOncv54OAO1ceO-I&width=576&height=324&externalId=espn:8420216&thruParam_espn-ui[autoPlay]=false&thruParam_espn-ui[playRelatedExternally]=true"></script>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Grit?]]></title>
    <link href="http://philcrissman.com/2012/10/09/grit/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-09T09:51:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://philcrissman.com/2012/10/09/grit</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The topic of &#8220;grit&#8221; is the focus of most of the most recent (<a href="http://5by5.tv/b2w/87">#87</a>) back to work. I&#8217;ve thought along these lines a lot. Like Merlin says a couple times, I feel like if I&#8217;m honest, I&#8217;m lacking in grit. Lack of grit has been an issue in accomplishing (or rather, not accomplishing) a lot of things I&#8217;d <em>like</em> to have done.</p>

<p>There&#8217;s something Merlin said in an early B2W episode that foreshadows this<a href="#one">1</a>, something said in the character of &#8220;that&#8217;s fine for Merlin&#8221;-guy, along the lines of, &#8220;You know, I just can&#8217;t do these things, because I&#8217;m, like, <em>not smart</em> and, like, <em>don&#8217;t try</em>.&#8221; The &#8220;don&#8217;t try&#8221; line is the one I&#8217;m thinking of here.</p>

<blockquote><p><a name="one">1</a> <em>This blog is not intended to be an exercise in &#8220;let&#8217;s comment exclusively on things Merlin and Dan have said in the the Back to Work podcast.&#8221; It just happens that this is maybe the podcast that I listen (and relisten) to the most, and it makes me think about things, and then I want to write about said things. If it comes across as just too sycophantic or something, well, I don&#8217;t think that&#8217;s anything I can help you with, maybe you should read something else.</em></p></blockquote>

<p>Can &#8220;grit&#8221; be developed? I want to believe it can, otherwise I&#8217;d have to resign myself to failure on a lot of areas.</p>

<p>What is &#8220;grit&#8221;? Definitions that came up were along the lines of: Self-restraint, being able to delay gratification. Stick-to-it-iveness.
<span class='pullquote-right' data-pullquote='Very little I&#8217;ve accomplished has been because of &#8220;grit&#8221;.'>
I&#8217;ve accomplished a lot of things by being fortunate, or blessed, or just in the right place at the right time. Very little I&#8217;ve accomplished has been because of &#8220;grit&#8221;.  At least, that&#8217;s how I feel when I look back.
</span></p>

<p>Now, since I just admitted I don&#8217;t have this &#8220;grit&#8221;, here&#8217;s some completely unqualified thoughts on what I imagine <em>might</em> be a way to develop &#8220;grit&#8221;:</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Narrow it down. You are just not going to be able to have a single minded dedication to all the dreams you could ever have. If you think you want to write a novel, go to law school after work, learn to program computers from scratch, learn to draw, work out and look like Arnold Schwarzenegger, and become president, well, you might need to just pick one of those and go for it. Or at least, one at a time. Someone is already reading this and mentally composing a response about how they can and will achieve all their dreams all at once. Which is great, but&#8230; For most of us, if we actually want to accomplish something, we should probably dial it down. I&#8217;m not saying &#8220;don&#8217;t havebig goals&#8221;&mdash;just, maybe, don&#8217;t have <em>20</em> big goals. Pick one. The hardest part, I think, is deciding what you really care about.</p></li>
<li><p>A blueprint. Figure out the plan. The whole plan. If you really want to write a novel, figure out how to do that. Sure, maybe read about it, that&#8217;s important, but don&#8217;t read about it so much that you never actually start doing it. Figure out who what where when how, figure out how many words a day you would need to write, or how many words you <em>can</em> write, and make a plan when each day you&#8217;ll do that. Then do that the first day. Then the second day.</p></li>
</ol>


<p><span class='pullquote-right' data-pullquote='This is the step where you simply keep at it, and it feels like a catch-22, like the way to have grit is just to _have grit_'>
3. ??? Around here&#8230; I don&#8217;t know this step. If I did, I guess I would be someone who already <em>has</em> grit. This is the step where you simply keep at it, and it feels like a catch-22, like the way to have grit is just to <em>have grit</em>, which sounds a little motivational speaky, but is also sort of true (at least in the sense that its a tautology). But what if my problem is, I don&#8217;t stick with things? How do I say, <em>this</em> is the thing that I stick with? You could focus on the goal, the finish line. That sounds like a thing that people say, people who talk about these things. But so, how do you <em>do</em> that?
</span></p>

<p>One thought could be, just continue to focus on your goal, on the &#8220;end&#8221; you want to arrive at. If you continue to focus on your &#8220;goal/end&#8221; (eg I want to have finished a novel) and if that vision is still not enough to get you to write a thousand or 500 or even 100 words a day, well, maybe you don&#8217;t really want to do this thing <em>that</em> badly. Sorry. Maybe you need to find a new thing.</p>

<p>See since we&#8217;re talking about novels (which I do actually want to write, and I&#8217;m beginning to think that maybe I actually don&#8217;t care about it enough to ever do it) I&#8217;m reminded of some advice I read in a writing book, I think it was by Lawrence Block. He said you should take a novel that you like, and dissect it. Use a series of colored pencils and highlight the entire book. Mark with one color where a new character is introduced, or where a goal or a conflict or (etc) happens, until you have dissected the structure/framework if the whole novel. Then just plain copy it. As if you we&#8217;re plugging in your characters for theirs, your story goals for theirs, your settings for theirs, and just write it. His point was, if you do this, it will be this sort of derivative copy novel that sort of sucks, but it <em>will</em> be a novel, with characters and a story and a beginning middle and end (because you straight out copied an existing work that had all these things), and you will have <em>finished</em> it, it will exist. Basically, write one to throw away. So, yeah, it will almost definitely be a bad novel and you won&#8217;t ever want to show it to anyone. But you will have done it, and you&#8217;ll have learned a lot about how a novel works and is structured and how it gets from point a to the conclusion.</p>

<p>Now here&#8217;s the thing: if you&#8217;re like me, you might have just read that, and think it makes sense and would work and you <em>still</em> think that you&#8217;re special and you can skip this step and just write your real novel. And if you&#8217;re like me, you still haven&#8217;t ever done it.</p>

<p>It takes grit to write an entire novel that you know will suck and no one will ever read or publish. But what if <em>doing</em> that meant that next, you really <em>could</em> write that real novel that you actually want to write?</p>

<p>Grit.</p>

<p>I&#8217;m not saying that the above strategy would work, though it probably wouldn&#8217;t hurt and is probably better than never writing anything, but it&#8217;s something to think about: the idea that if you aren&#8217;t willing to pay the price to reach your goal, well, maybe you just don&#8217;t care enough about that goal. Maybe you need a new goal. Selah.</p>

<p>What is the thing that, thinking about it as though it were really possible, as though it were real, could motivate you to take the steps to make it real?</p>

<p>Okay, I&#8217;ve spilled over into Tony Robbins territory, but think about it anyways. What is it that you care enough about to pay the price to make it happen? And if you don&#8217;t care about anything that much, what would that thing be if you <em>could</em>, and is there any way you could <em>make</em> yourself care that much about it?</p>

<p>If you don&#8217;t care that much about the think that you think you want to be your goal, try to imagine what it would feel like to care that much. Picture how you would feel if you were that sort of person. Again, more hippie motivational stuff. Throw it away if it sounds dumb to you. But you never know. It could help.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Nothing 'just happens'.]]></title>
    <link href="http://philcrissman.com/2012/10/03/nothing-just-happens/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-03T17:16:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://philcrissman.com/2012/10/03/nothing-just-happens</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>More from <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dave_Sim">Dave Sim</a>, this time from the <a href="http://www.cerebusfangirl.com/artists/nftp/185.php">Note from the President in #185</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>Self-publishing does not just happen. Even if I put everything that I know about self-publishing into a single volume and mailed a copy free to everyone who wrote in asking for advice, self-publishing would not just happen. One of the biggest obstacles you are going to face in trying to self-publish is your own inertia. Jeff Smith&#8217;s standard advice is to &#8216;do your homework&#8217;. By this he means that you should find out everything about publishing and distribution before you even attempt to enter the field. &#8216;Doing your homework&#8217; is very different, however, from the traditional view of that phrase, which has come to mean (in the last half of the twentieth century) send a list of thirty-five questions to an expert and then sit back and wait for a reply.</p>

<p>Understand this:</p>

<p>Not only doesn&#8217;t the world revolve around you, NOTHING revolves around you. You are a human being. Picture yourself as a planet. Your talent, your intended comic book, your story-to-be is your molten core. It is up to you to make an environment for that molten core which is conducive to growth, which will permit your talent to flourish in a hostile world. There are any number of ways to go about this. I always recommend that the story has to come first. You have to have something to say. The only way to find out if you have something to say and the determination and work ethic to see it through to its conclusion is to make a start and stick with it. I find, at this point, that most would-be self-publishers&#8217; eyes start to glaze over.</p>

<p>SNAP SNAP.</p>

<p>WAKE UP!</p></blockquote>

<p>Love this. For years before I left Full Time Employment and went freelance, I would always look at anyone who was self-employed, or a contractor, or working freelance, and be a little jealous, and I would want to ask them <em>how do you do that?</em>, by which I really meant, <em>how can I do that?</em> Invariably, I wasn&#8217;t happy with the answer(s) I recieved. I always felt like there was some sort of magic dust that I was missing which would help me to suddenly &#8220;go freelance&#8221;.</p>

<p>What the &#8220;secret sauce&#8221; actually turned out to be was to just <em>quit</em> a full time IT role at Oracle in exchange for a 3-month contract at a pretty low freelancing rate, because honestly, I really had no idea what I was doing at that point.</p>

<p><em>3 months?</em></p>

<p>Yeah.</p>

<p><em>But what did you plan to do after 3 months?</em></p>

<p>I had no idea. It turned out that the initial 3 months turned into 6 months, after which I was able to go do some work for a different local developer, and so on. In retrospect, I was incredibly fortunate. But I also would never have experienced that &#8220;good fortune&#8221; without just making a start, essentially jumping without a net. I&#8217;m still not sure how my wife dealt with the stress of my taking that leap. It&#8217;s worked out fine&mdash;better than we could have predicted, really, as I&#8217;ve been able to raise my rates substantially over the past 4+ years, and we&#8217;re now doing far better, financially, than if I had just kept my safe corporate job. My first freelancing contract was essentially a paid internship in Ruby on Rails and independent consulting and I&#8217;ll be forever grateful that I had that opportunity.</p>

<p>But there was certainly no way to predict that when I took the leap.</p>

<p>When I think about it now, it seems like one of the best decisions I&#8217;ve ever made. But prior to that, all my thinking and wishing about &#8220;going independent&#8221; was pretty much exactly what Dave Sim describes in the arena of self-publishing; I was hoping to find some nugget of knowledge, some magic step that would cause my indepence to &#8220;just happen&#8221;.</p>

<p>Nothing &#8220;just happens&#8221;.</p>

<p>Except maybe entropy.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[More Mortar than Brick]]></title>
    <link href="http://philcrissman.com/2012/10/03/more-mortar-than-brick/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-03T08:55:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://philcrissman.com/2012/10/03/more-mortar-than-brick</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As I create yet another of these, I felt like I should probably call these &#8220;summaries&#8221; rather than &#8220;reviews&#8221;. These are not &#8220;reviews&#8221; of <a href="http://5by5.tv/b2w">Back to Work</a> episodes; the &#8220;review&#8221; is, they are awesome and you should go subscribe to the podcasts at once.</p>

<h2><a href="http://5by5.tv/b2w/2">Picture of a Boat</a></h2>

<p><strong>Running time:</strong> 1:08:02</p>

<p><strong>Pairs well with:</strong> A dreamcatcher, some ambition, and a picture of a boat. (Dreamcatcher and picture of a boat are optional)</p>

<p>Dan and Merlin talk about dreams which cannot be interpreted on the air. Probably a sex thing.</p>

<p>The possibly canonical cognitive bias is revealed: that other people are stupid and mean, and I have my reasons.</p>

<p>On how Merlin is rarely rehired by companies because he often winds up telling them that the people who hired him are a big part of the problem.</p>

<p>Some chatting about the standard corporate rhetoric on innovation. Everyone wants you to innovate. But it&#8217;s not really a verb. There&#8217;s no &#8220;innovate&#8221; button on Merlin&#8217;s keyboard. If you really want innovation, you need to tolerate the sort if chaos and failure rate that often typifies environments where innovation happens.</p>

<p>Paraphrase: if you really did want innovation everywhere you need to encourage ambitious and crazy efforts that will probably fail.</p>

<p>On genetics: if your company culture doesn&#8217;t foster this sort of thing, that&#8217;s sort of like DNA and its going to be really hard to change. Find the little group in your company that ships the most interesting stuff and find out what it is about their team that makes them able to do that, an try to replicate the <em>spirit</em> that makes that possible. What do they not see as barriers that everyone else sees?</p>

<p>On empowerment: it&#8217;s a shame this concept even has to exist, it&#8217;s a shame people need to ask permission to be awesome.</p>

<p>Dand and Merlin talk about how many people tend to be conservative at work; not wanting to lose job, rock boat, not want to be the guy who came up with The Thing That Just Failed, everyone wants buy in from everyone else.</p>

<p><span class='pullquote-right' data-pullquote='The way you become CEO isn&#8217;t by showing up on time, you become CEO by being so great that the person 1-3 levels above you can&#8217;t keep you from being promoted over them.'>
Maybe you&#8217;re in a place with more mortar than brick. Maybe you aren&#8217;t expected to innovate. So then what? Go ship anyways. The way you become CEO isn&#8217;t by showing up on time, you become CEO by being so great that the person 1-3 levels above you can&#8217;t keep you from being promoted over them.
</span></p>

<p>What are you willing to sacrifice for that thing you care a lot about? Ego. Always being right. If you can&#8217;t take the trade off, then&#8230; You pretty much just need to move on (ie give up)</p>

<p>Stuff about <a href="http://www.cocoatech.com/pathfinder/">Path Finder</a> (app, Mac finder replacement).</p>

<hr />

<p>Great episode. Go thou and do likewise.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How Do I Become a Professional Golfer?]]></title>
    <link href="http://philcrissman.com/2012/10/01/how-do-i-become-a-professional-golfer/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-01T16:03:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://philcrissman.com/2012/10/01/how-do-i-become-a-professional-golfer</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://philcrissman.com/images/posts/cerebus168cover.jpg" alt="Cerebus 168" /></p>

<p>I&#8217;ve been re-reading <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cerebus_the_Aardvark">Cerebus the Aardvark</a> in its entirety; started at issue number 1 a few weeks ago. As I&#8217;ve gone through the issues, I&#8217;ve been reading Dave Sim&#8217;s <em>Notes from the President</em> column. In issue 168, he begins talking about <a href="http://www.cerebusfangirl.com/artists/nftp/168.php">the issue of self-publishing comic books</a>, and I was struck by how his first column on the topic contains advice that is really germane to almost <em>anything</em> that you want to do, but that you don&#8217;t yet know how to do.</p>

<blockquote><p>When young cartoonists ask me how to self-publish, I always liken it to a golf fan going up to Lee Trevino and asking &#8216;How do I become a professional golfer?&#8217; The answer of course is a question. &#8216;Do you have a set of golf clubs?&#8217; Here, let me write that down. Buy a set of golf clubs. And then a second question &#8216;Have you ever played golf?&#8217; Okay, that&#8217;s good. Let me write that down, too. Play some golf. Do you understand? Writing and drawing comic books is like anything else. You have to apply yourself and you have to do it. Assuming I wanted to be Eric Clapton when I grow up (or at least when I&#8217;m older), it makes a great deal of sense for me to buy a guitar and take some lessons before I write and ask him how to become like him. You first have to find out if you have the aptitude for what you&#8217;re attempting to do. Now, the only way that you are going to discover that is to sit down and try to do it. The guideline I always use is A Page a Day. If you can&#8217;t comfortably do a finished comic book page (written, pencilled, inked, lettered and toned) in a single day, you are facing trouble before you get very far along. Assuming that you are going to draw a comic book every month and making allowances for the way that life intrudes despite the best of creative intentions, a page a day is mandatory if you&#8217;re going to stay on your monthly schedule. If it takes you two or three days to do a page, the best that you&#8217;re going to manage is bi-monthly and if two or three days is the best you can manage and most of the time if takes you four or five days, then you are looking at quarterly as the maximum frequency. When you consider that the average black and white comic book is going to sell two or three thousand copies and the profits from that are going to be around two or three hundred dollars, that gives you a total income of seventy-five dollars a month for all of your living expenses. Even the most widely-known and well-thought of black and whites are selling in the low ten to twelve thousand range. It is not a get-rich quick scheme. The first five years that I did Cerebus I could have made more money baby-sitting (that isn&#8217;t a joke). Five years. Think about it.</p>

<p>But, I&#8217;m getting ahead of myself.</p>

<hr />

<p>The most common mistake of the starting cartoonist who wants to self-publish is to ask questions about things that are two or three years down the line. How do I copyright my character? How do I find a printer? How do I solicit the distributors? How much should I advertise? What you are doing is asking Lee Trevino (having already established that you don&#8217;t even own a set of golf clubs) what the best airline is to travel from tournament to tournament: how much caddies get paid; what sort of wood to use on the fifth hole at whatever course.</p>

<p>Go to the bank, take out some money, and buy yourself a club.</p></blockquote>

<p>I know, it&#8217;s ostensibly about making an independent comic book. Again, I think the core of the above advice applies to almost anything you want to do.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What couldn't you ship?]]></title>
    <link href="http://philcrissman.com/2012/10/01/what-couldnt-you-ship/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-01T08:47:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://philcrissman.com/2012/10/01/what-couldnt-you-ship</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I never used to listen to podcasts.</p>

<p>That ever so slight barrier to entry, the friction of having to actually subscribe to an RSS feed and take the time to plug in to iTunes or transfer things to a phone, always was just enough friction to stop me from bothering. That and the huge variety of available podcasts (even several years back, it seemed like there were innumerable podcasts out there), and <em>no idea</em> how to evaluate what I would want to listen to.</p>

<p>My friend Todd Emmel of <a href="http://slantwiselabs.com">Slantwise Labs</a>, who I was working for at the time, had started listening to a new show called &#8221;<a href="http://5by5.tv/b2w">Back to work</a>&#8221;, and asked me if I&#8217;d listened to it, or was aware of it. &#8220;Why, no,&#8221; I said. &#8220;What is it?&#8221; &#8220;It&#8217;s this new podcast that Merlin Mann is doing,&#8221; he said.</p>

<p>So, I knew exactly 3 things about Merlin Mann at that point. I knew he was behind <a href="http://43folders.com">43 Folders</a>, which I had not really heard of or read until about the time he stopped publishing regularly on it; I knew he was behind <a href="http://5ives.com">5ives</a>, which I thought was awesome and which had also stopped being updated; and I knew he had something to do with <a href="http://youlooknicetoday.com">You look nice today</a>, which I had heard wonderful things about and which I had never taken the time to listen to. And which had also stopped being updated.</p>

<p>So, Todd said this &#8220;Back to work&#8221; was really good. So I took the time to overcome the minimal friction between finding a podcast and actually listening to it, and downloaded the first handful of episodes (I think there were only 3 or 4 episodes published at the time).</p>

<p>Long story short, I&#8217;ve now been a listener for the past year+, and also listen to a handful of other podcasts, mostly also <a href="http://5by5.tv">5 by 5</a> podcasts, because they&#8217;re great.</p>

<p>Just because, I recently decided to go back and re-listen to all the B2W episodes. Unlike many podcasts which may focus, at least in part, on current events, B2W&#8217;s topics are generally contextless, which lends <em>very</em> well to relistenability. So this is the first of (possibly many) reviews of historical B2W episodes.</p>

<h2><a href="http://5by5.tv/b2w/1">The Alligator in the Bathroom</a></h2>

<p><strong>B2W S01E01</strong></p>

<p>Running time: 1:29:28</p>

<p><em>In which the genesis and premise of the show are discussed at length, and we are promised that Merlin intends to do more than 3 episodes. Also, Florida, San Francisco, kids, Buddhism, and ADHD.</em></p>

<p><strong>Pairs well with:</strong> 32oz of black coffee and 30mg of generic Adderall.</p>

<p>Still an episode worth a listen (or re-listen), despite the &#8220;sticking our heads up each others ass and saying how nice it smells&#8221; (Merlin&#8217;s phrase). It does, I thought, help to establish the context of how and why the show began and what both Merlin and Dan hope to get out of it, the &#8220;goals&#8221; and general topics of the show.</p>

<p>A phrase that came up was something along the lines of, &#8220;trying to become good enough that the people you really admire wouldn&#8217;t mind working on something with you.&#8221; Which is something that I had really never thought of, and did make me stop and think.</p>

<p>Another sort of blindingly obvious but still helpful, for me, observation, was the simple statement that if you want to mow your lawn, you can&#8217;t go to the movies. I.E., you really can only do a limited amount of things, and in order to to the things you really want, you&#8217;re going to need to choose the things that you don&#8217;t do. Leading up to: the higher up you go, the more opportunity you have to disappoint more interesting people.</p>

<p>Related takeaway: speaking of distraction; consider that if you have time to masturbate (assuming you have time for that), or to play video games, or to pick up your zombies on Facebook, you&#8217;re not really distracted. Selah.</p>

<p><strong>Notable:</strong> The phrase, &#8220;It&#8217;s your show&#8221; makes its first appearance right here in E01, albeit without the sharp passive aggressive undertone (or overtone) which it acquires later in the shows run. Also, &#8220;that&#8217;s fine for Merlin&#8221; guy shows up, though I don&#8217;t think that precise phrase is used in this episode.</p>

<p>Also, <a href="http://brettterpstra.com">Brett Terpstra</a> is referenced. But without the enaging, idiosyncratic pronounciation of his last name.</p>

<p>B2W E01. If you have never listened, it&#8217;s worthwhile to start right at the beginning.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Star Trek Ringtone]]></title>
    <link href="http://philcrissman.com/2012/09/07/star-trek-ringtone/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-07T14:26:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://philcrissman.com/2012/09/07/star-trek-ringtone</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I made this a long time ago, but since it&#8217;s about to be the anniversary of the first episode (September 8, 1966), here&#8217;s a ringtone I made, using a snippet from the infamous &#8220;battle/fight music&#8221; from the original series.</p>

<p>Download:</p>

<p><a href="http://philcrissman.com/assets/startrek.m4r">startrek.m4r</a></p>

<p>Listen before you download:</p>

<script type='text/javascript' src='http://philcrissman.com/javascripts/libs/swfobject-dynamic.js'></script>




<div id='mediaplayer'></div>




<script type="text/javascript">

   var flashvars = {
      'file':   '/assets/startrek.mp3',
      'controlbar':     'bottom'
   };
    
   var params = {
      'allowfullscreen':        'true',
      'allowscriptaccess':      'always'
   };
 
   var attributes = {
      'id':                     'playerID',
      'name':                   'playerID'
   };

   var callback = function(){};

   swfobject.embedSWF('/assets/jwplayer/player.swf', 'mediaplayer', '560', '24', '9', flashvars, params, attributes);
    
</script>



]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The song that changes everything]]></title>
    <link href="http://philcrissman.com/2012/09/05/the-song-that-changes-everything/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-05T21:52:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://philcrissman.com/2012/09/05/the-song-that-changes-everything</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>John Roderick talked in RoL E42, <a href="http://www.merlinmann.com/roderick/ep-42-your-hands-would-be-your-passport.html">Your hands would be your passport</a>, about his first time hearing the Beatles song <em>I am the walrus</em>. To paraphrase, he spoke of listening, speechless, staring at the radio, listening to &#8220;this insane music&#8221;, and how it changed everything. See around minute 7:46.</p>

<p>I had a similar experience hearing that song &#8211; I mean, it is a crazy scary song, and prior to that, I think I&#8217;d heard mostly short, happy songs from the Beatles.</p>

<p>But my only real parallel to that experience would be slightly before this, when I heard Led Zeppelin&#8217;s <em>Whole lotta love</em> for the first time.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>It&#8217;s probably hard to believe, but I made it to about the age of 17 without ever hearing Led Zeppelin. I&#8217;m sure I must have heard a song or two on the radio or in the background, but I didn&#8217;t know it to be Led Zeppelin. I was raised in a pentecostal Christian household, and we didn&#8217;t listen to rock music. Well, later we kids listened to <em>Christian</em> rock music. So, at about the age of 12, I thought Amy Grant was rock music. Soon after that it was other shining examples of Christendom&#8217;s rock outreach, like Petra, Degarmo &amp; Key, Mylon LeFevre, and so forth. Eventually it was Stryper. Yes, Stryper. If you know of these bands, you probably know they weren&#8217;t great, but they did play, I suppose, what for the 80s passed as a sort of rock &#8216;n roll music.</p>

<p>It was around this time that I began to hear <em>about</em> Led Zeppelin. See, I wanted to learn to play guitar, so I would read guitar magazines, and I learned that there was this giant in the history of modern rock and metal (this was about 1989, 90 maybe) called Led Zeppelin. So I was indoctrinated that Led Zeppelin was legendary, was awesome, were <em>giants</em>, and I more or less believed it whole-hearted, and I hadn&#8217;t even heard a single song. Without even hearing the music, I had built this legend in my mind of &#8220;Led Zeppelin&#8221;, and they had this mythological place in my thinking about rock music. Again, I still hadn&#8217;t even heard a song.</p>

<p>Eventually I began to seek out more music. This was the late 80s, remember. I had this habit of taking a blank cassette tape and listening to the radio and hitting <em>record</em> if I&#8217;d hear a song that I thought I&#8217;d like. Remember, again, the <em>only music I knew</em> was this 80s Christian rock. That&#8217;s about it. Overproduced (if not just badly produced), cheesy, not-necessarily-great-song-writing, derivative, bad. That&#8217;s all I really knew.</p>

<p>So this one night, Led Zeppelin comes on the radio. Not just any song, but <em>Whole Lotta Love</em>.</p>

<iframe width="420" height="315" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/Mln0RciE2o0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<p>I don&#8217;t know if I can properly communicate the impact of that song at that point in my life. The syncopation, the raw space and rhythm in that opening, was so alien to me, I was almost unable to process it as &#8220;music&#8221;. Plant&#8217;s shrieking was nothing short of scary. The rhythm of the opening and main guitar riff was so spare, so odd (I&#8217;d never heard <em>anything</em> remotely like it), I can remember not even knowing what to think. I imagine I was open-mouthed, shocked, alarmed, and in a little bit of awe and possibly confusion &#8211; this is <em>it</em>? <em>This</em> is Led Zeppelin? This is that legendary band? It sounded like the guitar was being hit with something, or wrung though a rolling pin (I don&#8217;t know if I knew then that Page was using a violin bow for some of that, probably not).</p>

<p>Then the guitar solo came in.</p>

<p>I mean the lick starting right after all the noise and weird sounds and Robert Plant moaning and screaming comes to that that crescendo, and there&#8217;s that sharp stop to two hard beats from John Bonham. (Right around the 3 minute mark, in the youtube video above) Then that series of licks, short bursts of notes in between the drum beats and over that steady high-hat tapping. Still one of my favorite guitar solos of all time.</p>

<p>I think I had to hear the song several more times before the whole thing really grew on me. But John Roderick, in relating his first time hearing <em>I am the walrus</em> reminded me of this. Every once in a while, you&#8217;ll hear something that utterly shatters your preconceptions of what music is allowed to do (years later, Fugazi&#8217;s <em>Repeater</em> was another one like that &#8211; yes, years later, I didn&#8217;t get into Fugazi until years after everyone else, so sue me).</p>

<p>I&#8217;m not sure everyone has had that experience. I mean, I think a lot of people have, maybe most people. But at the same time, I expect there are a lot of people whom, if you were to ask &#8220;What was that song which, the first time you heard it, changed everything?&#8221; &#8211; that there are a lot of people who just wouldn&#8217;t have an answer for that. Maybe music isn&#8217;t their thing, or they just don&#8217;t care that much, or maybe they&#8217;ve just forgotten.</p>

<p>On the other hand, I expect many people do have that memory. If you really like music at all, you probably have that moment filed away somewhere, that first time you heard the song that changed everything.</p>

<p>Postscript: can&#8217;t resist adding one more, possibly my favorite Zeppelin track, but that&#8217;s really hard to say:</p>

<iframe width="420" height="315" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/WbrjRKB586s" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Touching the stove, broken glass, and other peoples mistakes]]></title>
    <link href="http://philcrissman.com/2012/08/26/touching-the-stove/"/>
    <updated>2012-08-26T21:21:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://philcrissman.com/2012/08/26/touching-the-stove</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We&#8217;re supposed to learn from other peoples mistakes.</p>

<p>At least, this is what we&#8217;re told our whole lives. Those who fail to learn from history, we&#8217;re told, are destined to repeat it (possibly next semester). Eleanor Roosevelt said, &#8220;Learn from the mistakes of others. You can&#8217;t live long enough to make them all yourself.&#8221; Sounds like good advice. Who wants to make mistakes when they can be avoided?</p>

<p>But I distinctly remember having to touch the element on the top of the stove before I learned that I should have listened to my mom.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>We have a lot of literature in the field of Software Development which is basically &#8220;learning from the mistakes of others&#8221; wrapped in a bit of ceremony and jargon. Object oriented programming, design patterns, agile practices, XP, Scrum, code smells, refactorings, anti-patterns &#8211; all these things, at their core, are just one or more software developers saying to us: &#8220;Look. I&#8217;ve done this before. I&#8217;ve made mistakes. I&#8217;ve written large, unmaintainable systems, and I think we&#8217;ve found a way to avoid the mistakes we&#8217;ve made before &#8211; listen to this!&#8221;</p>

<p>Thankfully, this shared wisdom usually (eventually) gains a lot of traction. Other developers look into the patterns, the agile practices, the refactorings, and they see some of the pitfalls they themselves have fallen into in the past &#8211; or, may even still be falling into. You start getting wide-spread buy in into these ideas. They spread, they&#8217;re taught, they grow. We write manifestos, or sign them, and start to feel like we&#8217;re making some progress, like we&#8217;re figuring something out.</p>

<p>Somehow, though, once these things start to become entrenched, things get harder for the next generation coming in. The new programmers are handed a group of best practices, but they&#8217;ve never actually made or seen the mistakes that prompted the creation of these best practices in the first place. That makes some of these things seem silly, extraneous, or gratuitous. Why does this class &#8220;need&#8221; to be split into two classes? Cohesion? Who cares, really? Why should those methods be private, anyways? Why does my class need to be encapsulated?</p>

<p>I remember having these questions my first year of computer science; learning Java and (apparently) OOP. Only, we didn&#8217;t really learn OOP at all. We learned to type <code>public static void main(String[] args)</code> a lot. We never learned <em>why</em>. I remember being told that keeping methods private meant that we could hide the implementation from other classes, but I was never told why I would want this.</p>

<p>We usually do wind up seeing the wisdom, eventually, but we need to write some pretty bad code first. And even then, we may only see our mistakes if we&#8217;re lucky enough to recognize our mistake as something we&#8217;ve been warned about in the past, or if we&#8217;re fortunate enough to have a mentor who can point out where we went wrong, and what we might have done to avoid our mistake.</p>

<p>We need to actually make some of these mistakes, in order to learn from them. In order to see how much wisdom there is in some of this classic Software Development literature, we&#8217;re going to have to write some truly awful code.</p>

<p>I wish I could see a way around this; I&#8217;d love to think that we can just warn each successive generation of new software developers about the traps and snares and regions where there be dragonnes, but my experience and my gut tells me that this just isn&#8217;t going to work, compeletely. It&#8217;s good &#8211; I&#8217;m not saying we stop doing this. But I had to make some mistakes before I started to see how much smarts there was in the OOP model; before I started to realize the value of some design patterns. I had to write some bad code in order to see that certain things were, in fact, &#8220;bad&#8221;.</p>

<p>Even worse; some of these mistakes can only be made in large programs or systems. You can&#8217;t necessarily learn these things by writing a program to convert Celsius to Fahrenheit, and back. You need to amass some technical debt in a system which is actually supposed to go into production.</p>

<p>I want there to be another way, but I don&#8217;t think there is.</p>

<p>So, what then? Are we cursed with always having bodies of horrible code, perpetrated by each new generation of software devs as they stumble toward making better sofware?</p>

<p>Well. Probably. But hopefully, maybe, we can minimize it.</p>

<p>Just because we need to make <em>some</em> mistakes, doesn&#8217;t need we need to make <em>all</em> the mistakes over again each time.</p>

<p>If I&#8217;ve been told about patterns, about refactorings, about technical debt &#8211; then hopefully I&#8217;ll have a better chance of recognizing my mistakes the <em>first</em> time I make them (or at least, the second, or third) &#8211; rather than the fifth, or eighth, or tenth time I make them.</p>

<p>Now, that&#8217;s just the thing, about touching the red hot element on the top of the stove: I actually learned <em>two</em> things, there. First, yes, I learned that the stove was actually hot. But second, I learned that when my mom told me not to touch something, she wasn&#8217;t just making up arbitrary rules. Suddenly, it&#8217;s a lot more likely that I&#8217;ll listen to <em>other</em> things that she says. Why? Do I need to be hit by a car before I learn not to play in the street? Thankfully, no. I learned that she was telling the truth about the stove. Even as a five-year-old, this makes me think that hey, maybe mom knows a thing or two. Maybe I shouldn&#8217;t have touched the stove. Maybe I shouldn&#8217;t play in traffic, either.</p>

<p>Hopefully, if we combine reiterating these concepts about OOP, about patterns, about good software design, about Test Driven Development, then when we make mistakes, we not only recognize them faster, but all the rest of the advice we&#8217;ve been ignoring suddenly seems a little more important.</p>

<p>If I realize that my horrible unmaintainable mess of code was caused by violating principle <em>X</em>, maybe I&#8217;ll also take another look at principles <em>Y</em> and <em>Z</em>.</p>

<p>In the first edition of Obie Fernandez&#8217; <em>The Rails Way</em>, one of the technical reviewers made a comment in the section that was discussing the :include option for one of ActiveRecord&#8217;s class methods. Wilson said:</p>

<blockquote><p>Let people learn eager loading by crawling across broken glass, like we did. It builds character!</p></blockquote>

<p>The part of your brain that has always been told to &#8220;learn from the mistakes of others&#8221; rebels at a statement like this. But that little sidebar has stuck in my mind since I first read it, years ago.</p>

<p>Maybe there are some mistakes you <em>have</em> to make yourself.</p>

<p>Then the best thing we can hope for is that we have enough latent sofware development wisdom, somewhere in our heads, which we were taught (but ignored), that we can recognize we&#8217;ve made a mistake that many others have made before. A mistake that could have been avoided.</p>

<p>Maybe, rather than trying to set up new software developers so that they never need to make any mistakes, ever, we should set them up to make as many mistakes as possible, as soon as possible, and give them the tools to identify these mistakes so that they don&#8217;t need to make them again.</p>

<p>Maybe we can start to get better.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Thinking about Lift]]></title>
    <link href="http://philcrissman.com/2012/08/03/thinking-about-lift/"/>
    <updated>2012-08-03T08:37:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://philcrissman.com/2012/08/03/thinking-about-lift</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://philcrissman.com/images/posts/lift-icon.png"><img src="http://philcrissman.com/images/posts/lift-icon.png" width='320' /></a></p>

<p>Starters, <a href="http://lift.do">Lift</a> is a really nice app. It looks and acts great. It has a shiny checkbox that is large and round and easy to tap, and it has pretty graphs that look a little like graphic equalizers from mid-90s stereos with digital interfaces. I can choose a whole list &#8216;habits&#8217; which are then listed and shared, and if I check a habit for the day, then I can see all the other people who recently also did this habit. I can also give these complete strangers who have also seen fit to track their performance in consistent multivitamin consumption &#8220;props&#8221;, and can (in turn) receive &#8220;props&#8221; from them for performance of the same.</p>

<!--more-->


<p><a href="http://philcrissman.com/images/posts/lift-checkbox.png"><img src="http://philcrissman.com/images/posts/lift-checkbox.png" width='320' /></a> <a href="http://philcrissman.com/images/posts/lift-graph.png"><img src="http://philcrissman.com/images/posts/lift-graph.png" width='320' /></a></p>

<p>Then I will get a cheery email in my inbox the next day, Clarence459 has given you props for taking a multivitamin.</p>

<p>Thanks, Clarence459! It was rough, but I got it done. Now if only I can continue this arduous habit, I may be a statistical margin of error healthier when I&#8217;m eighty-four, so, I&#8217;m looking forward to that. Though, actually, the kudos are kind of nice. Who doesn&#8217;t like a pat on the back?</p>

<p>There is also the assumption that everyone everywhere will be more than happy to share their personal goals, and in particular share them with everyone else who is trying to accomplish the same thing. So I&#8217;m guessing &#8220;stop looking at porn on the Internet&#8221; will <em>probably</em> not be showing up in the list of habits any time soon.</p>

<p>That&#8217;s fine, though. It&#8217;s about affirmation, about things you want to change. I think most material about goals and habits would suggest that these things should ideally be positive and specific; not &#8220;Stop procrastinating&#8221; or &#8220;blog more&#8221;, but rather; &#8220;Work n hours&#8221;, &#8220;Write 1 blog post&#8221;, etc.</p>

<p><a href="http://philcrissman.com/images/posts/lift-list.png"><img src="http://philcrissman.com/images/posts/lift-list.png" width="320" /></a></p>

<p>This leads to another pitfall; when you first begin assembling your list of habits, you are shown the list of habits that other people have entered. It&#8217;s very easy to just start adding some habits, such as &#8220;Blog more&#8221;, because on seeing it you think, &#8220;Yeah, I actually would like to blog more. I should add this habit.&#8221; Not to get all motivational-speaker-goal-instructional, but that&#8217;s a terribly worded goal. More than what? If I have written one blog post in the last 6 months, then technically writing <em>two</em> blog posts in the next six months will be &#8220;blogging <em>more</em>&#8221;, but somehow I&#8217;m betting that&#8217;s not what we all had in mind when we checked off that habit. Once a habit is on your list, you have to take a bit of thought to remove it and replace it with a better worded habit. I mean, it isn&#8217;t hard, but there&#8217;s this thing you&#8217;d have to do and it&#8217;s really easy just not to bother.</p>

<p>Don&#8217;t misunderstand me, I like the app. I think a good list of positive habits than you can track to see how you <em>really</em> do at what you think you <em>should</em> be doing is a good thing. I can see it helping me reinforce some habits. I can even see the social aspect having some influence, though I&#8217;m not totally sold yet.</p>

<p>If you&#8217;d like to try Lift, visit <a href="http://lift.do">Lift</a>, or hit me up on <a href="http://twitter.com/philcrissman">twitter</a> and I can send you an invite. Even with an invite, I think they are rolling out the Beta in waves, so you might not get an invitation right away, but theoretically you might be higher in the queue.</p>

<p>I guess now I can go check off &#8220;Blog more&#8221; in my list.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Not far from the tree]]></title>
    <link href="http://philcrissman.com/2012/07/17/not-far-from-the-tree/"/>
    <updated>2012-07-17T14:08:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://philcrissman.com/2012/07/17/not-far-from-the-tree</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://philcrissman.com/images/posts/sam-laptop.jpeg"><img src="http://philcrissman.com/images/posts/sam-laptop.jpeg" width="440" /></a></p>

<p>Our son Samuel is almost 17 months old, now. He&#8217;s the coolest.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
