<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: regret | philcrissman.com]]></title>
  <link href="http://philcrissman.com/blog/categories/regret/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://philcrissman.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-10-19T15:51:32-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://philcrissman.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Phil Crissman]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Punk Rock]]></title>
    <link href="http://philcrissman.com/2012/10/16/punk-rock/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-16T08:35:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://philcrissman.com/2012/10/16/punk-rock</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/posts/usedtobepunkrock.jpg" title="I used to be punk rock" alt="I used to be punk rock" /></p>

<p>I'm not sure I ever was punk rock. On the other hand, I'm not sure I ever stopped.</p>

<p>It's complicated. It probably depends who you ask.</p>

<p>For me, the entire idea of punk rock isn't about the aesthetic, though there was a time when I sort of "fit" that mold (viz, "We all wear a uniform", Frank Zappa). It isn't about the politics. It isn't even (completely) about the music, as I <em>love</em> a lot of music that the original punk rock movement sort of rose up as a reaction against (John Lydon/Johnny Rotten was infamously reported to be discovered by Malcolm McLaren wearing a homemade <em>I hate Pink Floyd</em> t-shirt), though I do love a lot of punk rock music. What I really love about punk rock music is the backbone of integrity that it aspires to&mdash;at least, in my mind. A lot of people, among them folks who are "really" punk rock, might not see it the same way.</p>

<p>I think of it as distilling the entire notion of why I do what I do; why you do what you do, why anyone does what they do. In my mind, the motivation implicit in a "punk rock" mentality is that, I'm really not doing this for you. If you like it, that's great, and we can have this bond over this shared like of this thing that we're doing, but I didn't do it so you would like it. That oversimplifies, because sure, if you're producing things, whomever you see as "your people", yes, <em>of course</em> you hope that they like it. At least, I do. But at the same time, if you let other people's opinions be the sole barometer of the value of your work, I think you wind up with some blank, insipid creation that takes no risks and says nothing, and yeah, no one will like it anyways. Better to do something that at least <em>you</em> like, and then if only a handful of other people like it, at least it's genuine.</p>

<p>This makes me think of the whole idea of "selling out". Talking about this is a sure-fire way to stir people up. For some folks, simply "being successful" is synonymous with "selling out", which I think is (rightfully) seen as a pretty silly stance by most people. In my mind, it has more to do with <em>what were you willing to change in order to be successful</em>? Is this dumb, old fashioned? Don't we want success, at any cost? I don't know, but I think most people would say "no".</p>

<p>At the other extreme, I think some people think that there is no such thing as "selling out": no one should ever have their success criticized or impinged with accusations of lost integrity or compromised principles. It's none of our business, some would say. I can see that, in most cases, but I don't totally buy that, either. I'm not going to bring up examples, because I don't want to derail the discussion into a debate or who really <em>did</em> or <em>did not</em> "sell out"&mdash;but I can certainly think of bands who I stopped listening to, not because they became popular, but because the things they changed about their music on the way to becoming popular so completely altered their music as to make them into a completely different band; not the same band I had originally loved. It's not really just about "bands", though; anything can have integrity, and anything that has integrity can also lose it.</p>

<p>The idea of punk rock as an analogy to <em>integrity</em> might not be a usual association for most people, but it's incredibly valid to me. To me, the whole emotional impact of the phrase "I used to be punk rock" isn't "I used to have a mohawk and a safety pin in my ear, but now I don't"&mdash;it more says, "I used to have integrity, but now I don't". I realize this is a somewhat revisionist interpretation of "punk rock". One could just as easily say that "punk rock" ought to be associated with ideas of nihilism, anarchy, apathy, or rebellion. But ultimately, those aren't the things that I associate with 'being punk rock'.</p>

<p>Whatever.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
