<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: success | philcrissman.com]]></title>
  <link href="http://philcrissman.com/blog/categories/success/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://philcrissman.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-11-07T08:56:02-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://philcrissman.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Phil Crissman]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Arnold's Blueprint]]></title>
    <link href="http://philcrissman.com/2012/10/10/arnolds-blueprint/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-10T13:58:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://philcrissman.com/2012/10/10/arnolds-blueprint</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I saw this a week or two ago, and never even thought about posting it. But it's really relevant to everything else I've been thinking and writing about, so I thought I'd add it here.</p>

<div class="video-container">
  <script src="http://player.espn.com/player.js?&playerBrandingId=4ef8000cbaf34c1687a7d9a26fe0e89e&pcode=1kNG061cgaoolOncv54OAO1ceO-I&width=576&height=324&externalId=espn:8420216&thruParam_espn-ui[autoPlay]=false&thruParam_espn-ui[playRelatedExternally]=true"></script>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Grit?]]></title>
    <link href="http://philcrissman.com/2012/10/09/grit/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-09T09:51:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://philcrissman.com/2012/10/09/grit</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The topic of "grit" is the focus of most of the most recent (<a href="http://5by5.tv/b2w/87">#87</a>) back to work. I've thought along these lines a lot. Like Merlin says a couple times, I feel like if I'm honest, I'm lacking in grit. Lack of grit has been an issue in accomplishing (or rather, not accomplishing) a lot of things I'd <em>like</em> to have done.</p>

<p>There's something Merlin said in an early B2W episode that foreshadows this<a href="#one">1</a>, something said in the character of "that's fine for Merlin"-guy, along the lines of, "You know, I just can't do these things, because I'm, like, <em>not smart</em> and, like, <em>don't try</em>." The "don't try" line is the one I'm thinking of here.</p>

<blockquote><p><a name="one">1</a> <em>This blog is not intended to be an exercise in "let's comment exclusively on things Merlin and Dan have said in the the Back to Work podcast." It just happens that this is maybe the podcast that I listen (and relisten) to the most, and it makes me think about things, and then I want to write about said things. If it comes across as just too sycophantic or something, well, I don't think that's anything I can help you with, maybe you should read something else.</em></p></blockquote>

<p>Can "grit" be developed? I want to believe it can, otherwise I'd have to resign myself to failure on a lot of areas.</p>

<p>What is "grit"? Definitions that came up were along the lines of: Self-restraint, being able to delay gratification. Stick-to-it-iveness.
<span class='pullquote-right' data-pullquote='Very little I&#8217;ve accomplished has been because of &#8220;grit&#8221;.'>
I've accomplished a lot of things by being fortunate, or blessed, or just in the right place at the right time. Very little I've accomplished has been because of "grit".  At least, that's how I feel when I look back.
</span></p>

<p>Now, since I just admitted I don't have this "grit", here's some completely unqualified thoughts on what I imagine <em>might</em> be a way to develop "grit":</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Narrow it down. You are just not going to be able to have a single minded dedication to all the dreams you could ever have. If you think you want to write a novel, go to law school after work, learn to program computers from scratch, learn to draw, work out and look like Arnold Schwarzenegger, and become president, well, you might need to just pick one of those and go for it. Or at least, one at a time. Someone is already reading this and mentally composing a response about how they can and will achieve all their dreams all at once. Which is great, but... For most of us, if we actually want to accomplish something, we should probably dial it down. I'm not saying "don't havebig goals"&mdash;just, maybe, don't have <em>20</em> big goals. Pick one. The hardest part, I think, is deciding what you really care about.</p></li>
<li><p>A blueprint. Figure out the plan. The whole plan. If you really want to write a novel, figure out how to do that. Sure, maybe read about it, that's important, but don't read about it so much that you never actually start doing it. Figure out who what where when how, figure out how many words a day you would need to write, or how many words you <em>can</em> write, and make a plan when each day you'll do that. Then do that the first day. Then the second day.</p></li>
</ol>


<p><span class='pullquote-right' data-pullquote='This is the step where you simply keep at it, and it feels like a catch-22, like the way to have grit is just to <em>have grit</em>'>
3. ??? Around here... I don't know this step. If I did, I guess I would be someone who already <em>has</em> grit. This is the step where you simply keep at it, and it feels like a catch-22, like the way to have grit is just to <em>have grit</em>, which sounds a little motivational speaky, but is also sort of true (at least in the sense that its a tautology). But what if my problem is, I don't stick with things? How do I say, <em>this</em> is the thing that I stick with? You could focus on the goal, the finish line. That sounds like a thing that people say, people who talk about these things. But so, how do you <em>do</em> that?
</span></p>

<p>One thought could be, just continue to focus on your goal, on the "end" you want to arrive at. If you continue to focus on your "goal/end" (eg I want to have finished a novel) and if that vision is still not enough to get you to write a thousand or 500 or even 100 words a day, well, maybe you don't really want to do this thing <em>that</em> badly. Sorry. Maybe you need to find a new thing.</p>

<p>See since we're talking about novels (which I do actually want to write, and I'm beginning to think that maybe I actually don't care about it enough to ever do it) I'm reminded of some advice I read in a writing book, I think it was by Lawrence Block. He said you should take a novel that you like, and dissect it. Use a series of colored pencils and highlight the entire book. Mark with one color where a new character is introduced, or where a goal or a conflict or (etc) happens, until you have dissected the structure/framework if the whole novel. Then just plain copy it. As if you we're plugging in your characters for theirs, your story goals for theirs, your settings for theirs, and just write it. His point was, if you do this, it will be this sort of derivative copy novel that sort of sucks, but it <em>will</em> be a novel, with characters and a story and a beginning middle and end (because you straight out copied an existing work that had all these things), and you will have <em>finished</em> it, it will exist. Basically, write one to throw away. So, yeah, it will almost definitely be a bad novel and you won't ever want to show it to anyone. But you will have done it, and you'll have learned a lot about how a novel works and is structured and how it gets from point a to the conclusion.</p>

<p>Now here's the thing: if you're like me, you might have just read that, and think it makes sense and would work and you <em>still</em> think that you're special and you can skip this step and just write your real novel. And if you're like me, you still haven't ever done it.</p>

<p>It takes grit to write an entire novel that you know will suck and no one will ever read or publish. But what if <em>doing</em> that meant that next, you really <em>could</em> write that real novel that you actually want to write?</p>

<p>Grit.</p>

<p>I'm not saying that the above strategy would work, though it probably wouldn't hurt and is probably better than never writing anything, but it's something to think about: the idea that if you aren't willing to pay the price to reach your goal, well, maybe you just don't care enough about that goal. Maybe you need a new goal. Selah.</p>

<p>What is the thing that, thinking about it as though it were really possible, as though it were real, could motivate you to take the steps to make it real?</p>

<p>Okay, I've spilled over into Tony Robbins territory, but think about it anyways. What is it that you care enough about to pay the price to make it happen? And if you don't care about anything that much, what would that thing be if you <em>could</em>, and is there any way you could <em>make</em> yourself care that much about it?</p>

<p>If you don't care that much about the think that you think you want to be your goal, try to imagine what it would feel like to care that much. Picture how you would feel if you were that sort of person. Again, more hippie motivational stuff. Throw it away if it sounds dumb to you. But you never know. It could help.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
