<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: personal | philcrissman.com]]></title>
  <link href="http://philcrissman.com/blog/categories/personal/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://philcrissman.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-04-08T08:03:31-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://philcrissman.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Phil Crissman]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Seattle]]></title>
    <link href="http://philcrissman.com/2013/04/08/seattle/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-08T07:47:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://philcrissman.com/2013/04/08/seattle</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/posts/seattlehouse.jpg" title="zomg a house" alt="The new house. Don't be creepy" /></p>

<p>We've just moved to Seattle. Although I've already done moves from British Columbia (my home town, Surrey) to Tulsa, Oklahoma, and then from Tulsa to Minneapolis, Minnesota, this is definitely the hugest move I've ever done. When I moved from BC to Tulsa, I was living in a furnished single room that I rented from a family; so I left all my boxes behind and moved with a single suitcase and a duffle bag. Or something like that. When I moved up to Minneapolis, I had been in Tulsa for a few years, but I still moved with a minimum of "stuff": everything fit into the Nissan Sentra that I was driving at the time.</p>

<p><em>This</em> move, Amy and I have been married for 11+ years, have a 2 year old, and all kinds of stuff. What started as a plan to use a single 16' PODS container morphed into me renting a 26' UHaul, packing it to the gills, and then driving that 1700 miles towing a Mazda CX-9 on a trailer. Let's say I've decided to rule out "long distance truck driver" from my list of prospective mid-life crisis career changes.</p>

<p>That said, everything has gone pretty well. Made the drive in about 2 1/2 days. The folks at UHaul on MLK way were simply <em>awesome</em>, allowing me to park the (full) UHaul in their lot until I was able to actually move into the new house, giving me some additional small discounts, and just generally being an absolute pleasure to work with. They're getting a Christmas card this year. We had a friend of a friend of a friend find some guys who were willing and able to help unload the UHaul on a weekday, even knowing ahead of time that we had a piano (we have a piano).</p>

<p>Everything is still a little chaotic, but it's coming together. Looking forward to going to http://seattlerb.org tomorrow, if I can.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
